This is all public. Uh so, the
government once had a DARPA program
called LifeLog built to track every
email, every photo, every location,
every purchase a person made all in one
place.
They killed it on February 4th, 2004.
The next day, Mark Zuckerberg filed the
LLC for TheFacebook Incorporated.
Scale 1 to 10,
how much of a coincidence is that?
>> You know, a one or two.
Um
you know, there are some people, I'm not
one of them, maybe you're not one of
them, who are constantly thinking about
how to monetize literally everything.
>> Mhm.
>> They also have very deep connections in
government.
Well, we've known since Tom Drake went
public uh in 2002 that NSA is
intercepting every phone call, every
text message, every email. Okay.
Why not go farther than that and
intercept everything else? If DARPA was
doing it, he knew DARPA was doing it
because he has contracts in government,
sensitive contracts, and he knows that
they dropped it. Why not pick it up and
figure out how to monetize it? I believe
that's what happened.
>> Have you ever worked for Facebook?
>> Mhm.
But,
a guy that I worked with, my first job
at headquarters after I got back from
Athens,
guy had been chief of a gigantic
station. So, he was
well up there in the senior intelligence
service.
He resigned, and uh we were like, "What?
What do you mean you resigned?" He's
like, "You guys." He goes, "This thing,
this Facebook thing."
And I had like vaguely heard of it.
He said, "They made me an offer that was
ridiculous."
>> [laughter]
>> And then I never saw him again.
So, there are a lot of senior
CIA, FBI, NSA people that went to
Facebook and Instagram and Twitter and
LinkedIn and everywhere else.
>> Open AI recently.
>> Open AI. Will Hurd.
I don't know if you've ever heard of
Will Hurd.
>> He was the former
director of NSA?
>> No. [clears throat]
Will was
I mentored Will at the CIA. He was a
junior case officer, had a gift
for for for convincing people to commit
espionage, a gift.
Fun guy, sweet guy, really smart, funny.
He's half black, half white.
Decided to resign from the CIA to run
for Congress in a Supreme Court-mandated
majority Hispanic district.
And he won three times.
The races were close, but I'll tell you,
Will and I disagreed like had serious
disagreements on politics.
>> Mhm.
>> But the guy is as honest as the day is
long.
He ran for president for about a minute
and then dropped out in 20
Well, yeah, 2024.
And gave up his congressional seat to
run for president and ended up being on
the board of Open AI.
So,
yeah, he he authored
multiple cybersecurity bills
in Congress.
>> Parts of which were classified?
>> So,
he keeps one foot in the game and one
foot in business.
I'm not sure what he's doing. I know
he's making more money than he can
count.
And uh
I think is also
indicative of or an example of
the two worlds coming together. Keep in
mind also that in the immediate
aftermath of 9/11, the CIA got a waiver
from Congress
to open a venture capital arm called
In-Q-Tel.
Like how they're able to
how this is legal,
I have no idea.
But their very first investment,
$1,500,000
was to Palantir.
And now Palantir is
a multi-billion dollar
company.
It's involved in cutting-edge
technology, almost all of which is
classified.
A lot of people got very rich
going into Palantir and similar
high-tech  cyber organizations.
There's another company called Abraxas
Corporation.
Abraxas was formed in the '90s by a
bunch of guys that I used to work for.
And they set it up as a tax
pass-through. They didn't expect or
intend to make any money. They just
wanted a place where they could hang out
and drink coffee and smoke cigars and
talk about what great former CIA
officers they were.
And then they started putting in for CIA
contracts. Since they're friends with
everybody who is making the contracting
decisions, they started getting
um contracts, and the millions turned
into tens and then hundreds of millions
and then billions, and now everybody's
rich beyond his wildest dreams.
On the Palantir portion,
why does Palantir scare you?
Because there's no oversight of it.
We don't really know what Palantir does.
It's all secret. It's more than secret,
it's top secret. It's more than top
secret, it's top secret
compartmentalized.
So,
>> are the top secret compartmentalized?
Break that down for me.
>> Yeah. So, there are many levels above
top secret. They're they're
compartments. For For
when you join the CIA, everybody gets a
TS/SCI TK Gamma clearance. So, it's top
secret,
special intelligence, which is NSA,
talent, keyhole,
gamma. Those are three compartments that
everybody gets. So, let's say
most everybody in the military has a
TS/SCI.
Top secret sensitive compartment and
information.
Or SI, special intelligence. So, if NSA
just pick some phone call out of the
air,
you're cleared to see it.
If it is
sensitive, it's going to be talent
keyhole.
So, the military guy's not going to see
it. You get to see it. If it's gamma,
somebody with a special clearance gets
to see it. So, maybe I'll see it, but
you won't see it because maybe
maybe it's an intercept of a phone call
from some world leader,
right?
And then,
as another example, when I got back from
Pakistan, I was promoted to be executive
assistant to the CIA's Deputy Director
for Operations.
And in that position, you see literally
everything that is happening around the
world. I had
um TS/SCI
SI TK Gamma.
And then I added six more compartments
on top of that.
So, in fact, there was one morning
I was briefing the Deputy Director,
the Associate Deputy Director, and all
of the Associate Directors for
counterterrorism, proliferation,
counterintelligence, budgets.
So, I said,
"We have
a very important cable.
It's part of my normal morning briefing.
We have a very important cable
in the such and such compartment." And
the Deputy Director says, "Stop.
You and I are the only ones cleared for
that."
And I was like, "Oh my god, I'm so
sorry."
And he says, "Just give me the hard
copy." So, I gave it to him.
And I said, "None of the Associate
Deputy Directors for Operations
are cleared for the compartment?" And he
said, "No.
They don't have a need to know."
>> I want to
ask so badly what is the degree that
like someone like a Tulsi Gabbard has.
But
>> Well, that's a great question. Tulsi
Gabbard is supposed to have everything
of everything. She's the Director
of National Intelligence. So, she's the
overall Director of all 18
intelligence agencies in the US
government. Most countries have one or
two.
We have 18.
>> But it's it's a four-year term, right?
>> No.
>> So, you can be in that position for
>> You can be So long as you serve at the
pleasure of the President is the
language that they use. So, you can be
there for a day. You can be in there for
8 years or for 20 years if the President
decides you're doing a great job.
>> Mhm.
>> The truth is
>> [snorts]
>> until very recently, the DNI was really
in charge only of uh budgets.
That's it.
And even then, not really.
Because
because most of the intelligence
agencies in government are agencies
within the Pentagon.
NSA belongs to Pentagon, Army
Intelligence, Navy Intelligence, Marine
Corps Intelligence, Air Force
Intelligence, Coast Guard Intelligence.
They're all Pentagon.
So, they're part of the Pentagon budget.
So, the DNI is in charge of
intelligence, but no, actually no. The
State Department's Bureau of
Intelligence and Research
reports to the State Department. They
sit in the State Department. There's an
Assistant Secretary for Intelligence and
Research.
So, the DNI doesn't even really control
that.
>> How often would you say Trump gets asked
something and someone says, "That's
classified"?
>> I would really hope that that would
never happen.
I will tell you though
that there were times in my career
where
something would happen. Not a lot of
times, two or three.
Something would happen and
either the station chief
or the DDO, Deputy Director for
Operations, would say, "You know,
let's not put that in writing."
And so, there was no written record of
it. I'll give you an example.
I worked a case
where we recruited this guy. He was
incredibly dangerous.
Um he was a career criminal, a heroin
addict.
But he did this really cool thing for
us.
And so, we paid him very handsomely.
And I said to him,
"Don't spend all the money in one place
because it's going to raise eyebrows and
people are going to think you're
probably taking, you know, CIA money."
And he said,
"I'm going to use it to
marry my girlfriend."
I said, "Oh, that's terrific. That's a
great idea. Congratulations."
Couple of weeks later,
I work my normal day. I get home. I turn
on the news.
I see the guy on the news.
He's in cuffs.
He just shot his girlfriend's father.
It turned out
he went to ask the old man's
permission to marry his daughter.
And the guy's like, "I'm not marrying
I'm not letting my only daughter marry a
a
heroin-addicted career criminal."
And the guy just shot him in the face.
And he got arrested.
I called the station chief and I I was
like
"Are you watching the news?" He's like,
"No."
I said, "AB Grasshopper, I'm just making
that up.
There is no such thing as AB
Grasshopper. AB Grasshopper just shot
his girlfriend's father in the face. He
killed him. It's on the news." He's
like, "Oh my god. We have to inform
Congress."
So, I said, "Okay, I just got home. I'm
going to get back in the car and go
straight back to work."
I get back to work. He gets to work and
he's like, "You know,
on second thought,
let's not put that in writing."
I said, "Are you sure? Like, the rules
are pretty clear.
You got a recruited asset who's just
committed a cold-blooded murder."
He's like,
"They They wouldn't understand the
nature of our relationship with the
guy."
I was like, "You're the boss."
So, I didn't put it in writing.
I'd assume that's rare, though.
I would hope it's rare. Like I say, it
only happened to me one or two times and
I had
kind of a career that was out there.
Another program that
you've talked about quite extensively,
so
I'll ask about it in a different way.
Project Mockingbird, the CIA paid
journalist,
news anchors maybe, to report on what
they
wanted them to or change stories,
something along those lines. I can't
remember the exact details, but if you
had an unlimited budget and were running
Project Mockingbird right now, where
would you make sure you put that money?
Oh, overseas.
It should be patently illegal
to
propagandize the American people.
It was until Barack Obama changed his
mind in 20
15.
Oh, so that's recent. Oh, yeah. It's
recent.
You know, since since 1975, we haven't
been allowed to We I say we like I'm
still there. The CIA has not been
allowed to recruit journalists.
Uh American journalists.
So, the Church Committee
was appalled that the CIA was
was running this thing, Project
Mockingbird. And the Church Committee
made it illegal
to
to do that, to to recruit American
journalists.
It is perfectly legal.
It is actually encouraged
for you to
recruit foreign journalists.
With the idea being that you pay these
guys a handsome wage,
and they're going to plant pro-American
stories.
And also, they're going to tell you what
it has ended up on the cutting room
floor that might be important for, you
know, the CIA analysts or for an
operation that might be ongoing or
whatever.
The first time the CIA ever did this
was in the Italian election of 1949. It
was the very first covert action
operation.
The CIA spent $150,000
to bribe Italian journalists because the
Communist Party was ahead in the polls.
And they bribed these journalists to
write
articles that were in support of the
conservative um Christian Democratic
Party. And the Christian Democrats won
by a whisker. So, the CIA essentially
stole the 1949 Italian elections.
The CIA then began recruiting
journalists all around the world.
Mockingbird was different in that it was
geared toward recruiting American
journalists.
Well, it it was illegal to propagandize
the American people.
Americans weren't even allowed to listen
to the Voice of America.
I I you could if you had a shortwave
radio, you could hear it, but it's
propaganda. It's pro-American
propaganda. It's a government's
own radio voice.
Until 2015,
in the National Defense Authorization
Act of 2016,
that was rescinded, and it was rescinded
for the worst reason.
Have you ever heard of Radio TV Marti?
Mhm.
So, in the '70s,
the um
what became known as the Broadcasting
Board of Governors created a radio and
TV station, Radio Marti and TV Marti, to
beam anti-communist
propaganda at Cuba.
So, Radio Marti
was broadcast from a plane.
I actually went up in the plane at in
2011 when I was with the Senate Foreign
Relations Committee, and they just fly
back and forth in international airspace
between Florida and Cuba, and they
broadcast Radio Marti. Radio Marti is
mostly baseball games in Spanish. The
Cubans love baseball even more than we
do.
And so, they everybody tunes into the
baseball game. Sometimes the Cuban
government will jam the frequency,
um
but most people listen to it just for
the sports coverage.
TV Marti
is almost always jammed. You can watch
it in the waiting room at the American
Embassy when you're waiting for your
visa,
and it's you know, Miami Cubans yelling
about communism and
silly stuff like that. So, nobody
watches it.
Well, in the early aughts,
um it was picked up by the Dish Network.
And
the way the Dish Network broadcasts,
there's this little tiny sliver right
along the coast of southwestern Florida
where if your dish is like just right,
you can pick it up.
But it's illegal to propagandize the
American people.
And so the Obama administration said,
"You know what? Rather than make the
Dish Network change their frequency or
whatever, let's just make it legal to
propagandize Americans."
And so in the National Defense
Authorization Act of 2016,
they make it legal to propagandize
Americans. And so now you're if you're
on that little strip of coast of
southwestern Florida, you can watch TV
Marti. Not that anybody would want to,
but it also gives the government the
right
to essentially recruit American
journalists again. And I'll give you
another example. I have a friend who is
an absolutely fantastic investigative
journalist, Jason Leopold. He's now at
Bloomberg.
Jason
is the king of the Freedom of
Information Act.
He was once called by the Pentagon
spokesman during the Bush
administration, he was called a FOIA
terrorist
because he has filed more Freedom of
Information Act requests than any other
person on Earth.
So he told me
he's actually the guy
who broke the Hillary Clinton email
story.
Right? So he told me that he was bored
one week between Christmas and New
Year's. And he has this masterful way of
doing this.
The Freedom of Information Act says that
when you file the request, the
government has 60 days to respond.
Okay, I filed a request in 2015. I'm
still waiting for the response. They
never respond. So on day 61, you have to
file a lawsuit against them.
And they always lose. And they always
have to pay your legal fees. But nobody
thinks to do it, and people are too
busy. I'm too busy, and I don't really
care at the end of the day. It was about
one guy who was a science fiction
writer.
So anyway,
Jason has an attorney on staff. Not
staff, on on retainer.
And every time he files a FOIA request
on day 61, they sue.
They sue the CIA every time.
So, he said he's bored one Christmas
and he files a Freedom of Information
Act request for all communications
between the CIA
and all reporters over the previous
year.
Day 61,
he sues.
He wins.
The judge orders the CIA to release the
information and to pay his legal which
is the way it always is.
And he says he got back this mountain of
emails between the CIA's Office of
Public Affairs
and journalists from all around the
world. He said there were a couple that
were especially interesting.
>> What year was this?
>> This was
11, 12.
He said one of them was an exchange
between the CIA and Ken Dilanian of NBC
News. Ken Dilanian is the chief national
security correspondent for NBC News and
MS Now.
Ken Dilanian was writing articles
and sending them to the CIA for
clearance before sending them to his own
editor.
So, the CIA could say, "Yeah, take that
line out. You might want to change this
paragraph.
Don't say that. Say this instead. That's
propaganda."
They're propagandizing the American
people. I don't want to know what the
CIA's official line is. I want the news.
The other thing he found was there was
this young
hungry independent journalist
who actually had stumbled onto a real
story.
And he wrote up the story, he sent it to
the CIA, "Please comment. I'm going to
post it, you know, the next day." And
they wrote back and they said, "So help
us God if you publish this, you will
never be invited to the CIA Christmas
party ever again, and we will never give
you any background information.
And so he killed his own story.
So you don't need to
recruit American journalists anymore.
They do it for free.
Some of them do it just cuz they want to
be, you know, insiders with the guys.
Some do it because they're afraid.
So you don't need to recruit them
anymore.
>> That's an interesting one. I guess
I don't know why I'm
even thinking about defending the
original position of it, but just the
only thing that would make sense to me
is if the foreign people are trying to
get our journalist, then we might as
well try to get our journalist, too, to
kind of balance that out. Like did
Do you think that's fair or
>> would be an FBI program.
>> Right. That's That's what's strange to
me is the overlap of those two things.
>> forbidden from operating domestically,
unless it's overt. Certainly, the CIA
has offices all around the country.
Uh it's called National Resources
Division.
But their job is, let's say you're the
CEO of a company, and you go to China,
and you're negotiating with these
Chinese government people. The CIA is
going to call you and say, "Hey Jack, we
know you went to China recently. Do you
mind if we come by the office and ask
you a couple of questions about these
Chinese people you were dealing with?
You know, tell us about their
personalities, or do you know anything
about their backgrounds?" And because
you're a patriotic American, you say,
"Of course, come on over."
And then they go and they write
everything down. That's overt.
There's nothing secret about that.
Um but otherwise, they're not allowed to
operate on
on American soil.
>> Hm.
>> That's up to the FBI.
>> Maybe I haven't been looking for it, but
I feel like I haven't seen
as much about the FBI as I have the CIA.
>> No, you're right.
>> What's with that?
>> Yeah, it's funny. I think because so
much of what the CIA does is secret,
people's imaginations kind of start
working.
And
they're more likely to go down a rabbit
hole on the CIA than the FBI.
I think that's what it is. People are
always intrigued by what they're not
supposed to know.
And so they want to get to the bottom of
things.
>> Which do you think is the more
interesting rabbit hole?
>> Within the CIA?
>> The Just between the CIA and the FBI.
>> Mhm, counterintelligence, definitely.
Definitely.
Both the CIA
and the FBI have gigantic
counterintelligence
organizations. In the CIA, it's the
Well, now it's
It's Well, at the time that that I was
there, it was called the
Counterintelligence Center, CIC.
>> Mhm.
>> Its job is to find moles
inside the CIA.
It's the most highly classified work
that's done. Period.
The
FBI has what's called the National
Security Division.
And their job is also to look for moles.
And there are
There are more
people in government working for foreign
governments than than you might think.
It wasn't just Aldrich Ames and Robert
Hanssen, two traitors working for the
Russians.
Both of whom were the chief of
counterintelligence
for Russian operations,
by the way.
The Chinese are all over us,
you know? The mayor of Arcadia was just
arrested for being an unregistered agent
of the Chinese government and planting
pro-Chinese propaganda in Arcadia's
newspaper.
What's up with that?
Um another one is
all these Chinese PhD students that are
getting degrees in in the hard sciences
here. And then they say, "Oh, we love it
so much here. We're going to get green
cards. We're going to get American
citizenship. We're going to apply for
jobs at DARPA."
Come on.
Come on. They do it all the time.
>> They pay extra for the universities, so
[snorts]
>> They pay full price.
>> Yeah, there's some incentive there.
>> there is.
>> You said Epstein was likely an asset for
Mossad.
Based on what you actually know about
how the CIA and intelligence agencies
work, is it more likely that Epstein was
an asset for an intelligence agency
or that the intelligence agencies
were working for him?
>> Mhm.
I hadn't thought of it like that.
I hadn't really thought of it like that.
With this most recent tranche of
documents,
it solidified my belief that at the very
least he was working for Mossad. What we
learned in this
And you know what, let me explain that.
I've explained it in other in other
podcasts, but
if you're a foreign intelligence service
and you want to know what the most
important people in the country are
thinking, the the multi-billionaire
businessmen, the former presidents, the
number six in line to the British
throne,
etc.
You're not going to recruit those
people.
They don't want or need your money.
They're not going to tell you what you
want to know.
So, you do the next best thing and you
recruit a person with ready access to
them. And if they've got a weakness,
like we've heard, for example, Bill
Gates has.
Um
even better.
So, you recruit somebody like Jeffrey
Epstein. Keep in mind, we don't have any
idea the source of his money.
No idea at all.
I talked to a
a former journalist for the uh
New York Post.
And she said the first time Jeffrey
Epstein ever popped up
in her career was in the 1990s.
He had agreed to finance the purchase of
the newspaper The New York Sun.
And
her editor at the post said
"Figure out who this guy Epstein is. We
don't have anybody We don't have any
information about him in our files."
So, she said she called him and asked
for an interview. He hung up on her. She
called other rich people around town.
They were like, "We've never heard of
this guy." This is in the This is like
the
1997,
'96, whatever it was.
She couldn't find anything.
And so, finally, in the article, she
told me she wrote um
that the deal was backed by financial
mystery man Jeffrey Epstein.
And then she forgot about him until he
got in trouble and was in the papers for
that reason.
So,
could the money have come from a foreign
intelligence service? Of course, it
could have. Could it have come from Les
Wexner?
Certainly, it could have. Or from the
the Rothschild family?
Of course.
But we don't know for sure.
Um
we know from this latest tranche of
documents that Epstein was working on
behalf of the Israelis. But
he was probably working on behalf of the
CIA as well, the FBI, MI5 and MI6 in the
UK, the Germans, we think.
And he had tried repeatedly
to get in front of Vladimir Putin.
To the point where the Russians offered
him a meeting with Putin and two other
officials, and he said, "No, it has to
be just Putin." They said, "Forget it."
And so, he never met with Putin.
So, I think he was more likely
more likely than being
uh an access agent
that he was an intelligence broker.
Somebody who collects intelligence
and then sells it to different
intelligence sources, intelligence,
rather, agencies.
>> Would you say the wealthiest people in
the world
do that occupation?
>> Yeah, sure. Some of them. Look at
Ghislaine Maxwell and her family. Her
father had all the money in the world,
and he was an avowed, acknowledged
Israeli spy.
Um
>> But, do they start off in intelligence,
typically?
>> No.
No, they're brought in, typically.
Although, I will tell you
that a lot of them have a very deep um
interest in intelligence. When I was at
the CIA
I was married to another uh another
senior CIA officer.
We got invited
to dinner at the five-story
Park Avenue home
of a Fortune 50 CEO.
And I was like, "Why in blazes would
this guy want to have dinner with me?"
So, we went to dinner.
And it was perfect in every respect. He
had this staff of like 12 just standing
there like to be your personal slave for
the whole dinner.
And at the end of it, he walked us out.
And um
and I thanked him. I shook his hand, and
I said, "I've got to ask you
why did you want to have dinner with us.
And he says,
"Every CIA officer probably wishes he
was a billionaire.
I can tell you every billionaire wishes
he was a CIA officer."
And I thought, "Huh,
you learn something new every day."
He just wanted to
hear stories,
you know, lay out a couple of
ideas of his own.
>> Mhm.
>> The money after a while it's not so
important to them.
They start thinking back
about all the things that they could
have done,
something that was more exciting.
>> Have you ever spied on a secret society?
>> No. I actually get that question a lot.
>> Really?
>> Yeah.
I have a good friend who's an
investigative journalist,
but she's an she's an independent
investigative journalist making a
handsome living for herself, but she
kind of tends toward conspiracy
>> theories?
>> And I always
try to make her back down,
and then she always
proves that she was right and I was
wrong.
Drives me crazy.
So,
for the last couple of years, she's been
all about
the Masons.
And I'm like, "Will you leave the Masons
alone? I know a couple of Masons, and
all they do is raise money for
scholarships.
That's it. It's just a bunch of old men
that get together once a month and play
poker and raise money for scholarships."
And then
and then she starts developing some
information that I'm like, "Ooh, really?
Really?" And then she'll lay it out. And
then she goes deep into the histories of
some of these organizations. They were
all founded by the same circle of
people,
you know, on Wall Street or in the
immediate aftermath of World War I.
And then I have to admit that, "Okay,
there may be something to it. But no, I
never had to try to infiltrate a secret
society.
On the contrary,
there were a lot of guys at the agency
who were members of secret societies.
I'll I'll tell you one funny aside.
I happen to be Greek Orthodox.
And I went to There's one There's a
peninsula in northern Greece called
Mount Athos.
Uh Ayion Oros, the Holy Mountain.
And it's the home of 32
monasteries.
Uh it's the only place in the European
Union that is exempt from European Union
laws. And no women are permitted there.
They even remove female animals that
they capture.
So, I went there.
And I went to the first monastery.
You're allowed to go for 4 days and 3
nights. You have to get a special visa
from the Ministry of Religious Affairs
or whatever it's called.
So, I went I wanted to see the the
place, check it out. So, I get my visa,
I go.
And uh as soon as you get to the first
monastery, this priest comes out and
says, "Have you had confession today?"
I said I said, "No, I just got here."
"Okay, confession." I'm like, "Okay."
Well, in Greek Orthodox churches in
America,
you just sit there
and you tell the priest, "I did this, I
did that, I did the other thing." And he
says, "Okay, you're forgiven. You know,
go about your business."
It's different in Greece.
They read a list of sins.
And it starts with murder. "Have you
committed murder?" I'm like, "No."
"Rape?" "No." "Robbery?" "No." And I'm
thinking, "What's he doing?"
So, he says, "I have to read the list of
sins." I said, "Oh, okay." So, he's
reading this whole list. I'm like, "No,
no, no, no."
At the end he says, "Are you a member of
any secret societies?"
And I said, "No."
Well,
I'm a member of a fraternity.
And he says,
"Is it secret?" I said, "Well, we've got
a silly, you know, secret handshake."
He said, "That's a sin." I said, "Come
on, Father." I said, "The archbishop's a
member."
And he says, "Then the archbishop needs
to go to confession."
So, I'm like, "Okay, I'm a member of
secret society."
Want to join the CIA,
they asked me, "Are you a member of any
secret societies?" And I said, "No."
But then they specifically asked me,
"Are you a member of any fraternities?"
>> Mhm.
>> And I said, "Yeah, I'm a member of this
fraternity." "We never heard of that
one." I said, "It's just a bunch of
guys. We play poker once a month. We
order pizzas, and then we throw in, you
know, $100 for for scholarships for poor
children."
And they're like, "Oh, okay. All right."
And then they left it.
And I wonder if there was more to it now
in retrospect.
You know, what were they getting at? Did
they want me to be a member of a secret
society?
I don't know.
>> Those people that were,
were they when they joined?
>> Yeah.
Yeah, because they have these like
degrees, right? So, they're like, you
know,
60th degree, whatever.
And it takes you a lifetime to get up to
that position.
>> On your
past relationships, uh
do you think
Angry Birds led to your divorce?
>> No.
I think Angry Birds was a convenient
excuse for divorce.
You know,
in defense of Angry Birds
and my obsession with Angry Birds, I'm
proud to say
I have not missed a single day in almost
9 years.
I'm coming right up on 9 years of Angry
Birds every single day. I freaking
>> 3,000 yet?
>> Uh I'm 2,800.
I can show you on my phone. Today 2,879.
Something like that.
>> Wait, is it the original Angry Birds?
>> No, it's Angry Birds 2.
>> Mhm.
>> I love the original.
>> What's your favorite bird?
>> Angry Birds 2 is better.
>> [gasps]
>> You know, it's hard to say what my
favorite bird is.
Um, I always love the black one cuz he
explodes.
But, um, but there are a couple of new
ones. One that sucks everything up and
then spits it out. That's a good one.
And the latest one that spins around and
knocks stuff down. Very powerful bird.
So, I'm I'm devoting all my new feathers
to him so I can get him up. I I'm I'm
obsessive in the respect that I need for
all my birds to be exactly the same
level.
And so, um, I'll focus just on this
specific bird.
>> Do you know what you're ranked in the
world?
>> Um,
it's it's high up there.
Yeah. I'm I'm at the point where I'm not
ranked by stars anymore. I'm in the like
senior global senior league.
>> [laughter]
>> That was the most interesting thing I
saw when I started seeing you talking
about Angry Birds. I was like, I haven't
played that game in a while. I I hope
they sponsor this guy
>> I [laughter] You know what? I should
probably say something. I love it. I
love it.
>> it.
>> Angry Birds did not lead to my divorce.
I woke up I wake up an hour earlier than
I need to every day just so I can play
Angry Birds for the first hour. I don't
even get out of bed. As soon as I wake
up, I put my glasses on, I pick up my
phone, I go to Angry Birds, and it takes
me an hour to do all the daily games.
Um, that was just an excuse that a
former spouse used
to try to justify, you know,
the current situation.
>> Yeah, that's some that's some [__]
My wife and I, we we have arguments, of
course, like any couple, but uh, uh
she does not talk about me playing. I I
play this game called Clash Royale. It's
kind of like Clash of Clans. Have you
heard of this one? Do you play it?
>> No.
>> Hm.
>> But it looks good. I actually downloaded
it and I never started it.
>> You got to get into it. It's It's like
chess, but there's a little more luck
involved, so you don't have to
you can have an excuse for losing,
pretty much, you know what I mean? Um
but you've been married and divorced
twice.
>> Twice.
>> Do you ever wonder
if the CIA played a role
in anyone's divorce?
>> The CIA played a role in my divorce.
I apologize that by court order I'm not
at liberty to explain that,
but the CIA had an active role in my
divorce.
>> What did you say to your wife
the night before you went to prison?
>> I apologize. I I probably shouldn't say.
>> Hm.
>> Yeah, I shouldn't say.
That was a That was a terrible night.
I barely slept a wink.
Cuz you know, the there there's We all
have this natural fear of the unknown.
And I didn't know what I was getting
into.
At my sentencing, my attorneys asked
that I be sent to a minimum security
work camp.
And at the minimum security camps, there
are no fences, no bars on the windows,
the doors are unlocked, you're free to
just come and go as you please. You're
just on your honor not to abscond.
>> Hm.
>> And most of those guys
work in town at the university. There's
a small university.
And um you know, they're janitors or
what have you.
Um
the judge asked the Justice Department
if they had any objection. They said no
objection. The judge says
minimum security work camp.
So I got to the prison.
And um
I went to the camp, knocked on the door.
It's weird
unless they just take you into custody
and ship you to a prison,
they send you a letter and they say,
"Report to this prison on this day at
this time."
And you just drive up there
and knock on the door and turn yourself
in.
So, I knock on the door. I said, "I'm
I'm John Kiriakou. I'm here to turn
myself in." The guy says, "Oh, you got
to go across the street to the actual
prison. Then they put you through the
metal detector and then they walk you
back over here." I said, "Okay, great."
So, I go across the street, knock on the
door. I'm John Kiriakou. I'm here to
turn myself in.
He puts me through the metal detector
and then starts leading me around to the
back of the prison and I said, "No, no.
I'm at the camp across the street." And
he goes, "Ha.
Not according to my paperwork, you're
not."
And I was like,
"Take it easy. Don't say anything.
They'll put you in solitary." I didn't
say a word.
So,
it took me 4 days to get access to a
phone
and I called my lead attorney and I
said, "Hey, they put me in the actual
prison
with the mafia dons and the drug
kingpins and the pedophiles." I said,
"What do I do?"
He's like, "Oh my god." He said, "Buddy,
we could uh file a motion, but it'll be
2 years before we get a hearing and
you'll be home by then." He said, "I'm
sorry. You're going to have to tough it
out."
I was like, "Dang it." I said, "Okay.
I'm trained for this. I've lived in way
worse places than this.
I can do it."
And so, I did it.
I used my CIA training
to keep myself safe and at the very top
of the social heap.
>> Why do you think
no one ever made you
disappear?
>> I'm not sure.
>> [laughter]
>> But I I I have a I have a I have a
theory.
I have a theory
that
that I'm so high profile
that it would just be too obvious
what happened.
I'm not blind. I saw what happened to
Charlie Kirk.
Um so I've taken, you know, steps to
protect myself, certainly.
And I get death threats like a lot of
other people do.
Um and I take them seriously.
But um you know, this is one of the
reasons one of the two reasons why I
really want and need a presidential
pardon.
I've applied for one.
But uh in addition to losing my federal
pension, which I really really would
like to have back,
I want my guns back.
I need to protect myself.
And so, you know, when people write me
emails saying I can't wait to see your
brains splattered out in front of and
then they give me my home address,
I have to take that seriously.
>> Right.
>> So, I don't know.
I think that
it's a combination of things. I think
I'm too high profile that I would be
missed. And to tell you the truth,
all of my detractors are either dead or
retired.
I have a
a young friend who's at the CIA now.
I I try to advise a lot of young people
who apply for the CIA. I'm a realist. I
know the CIA is not going anywhere.
And so,
you know, if there's going to be change,
it has to be change that comes from the
inside.
So I'm I'm proud to say that there are
six people
who have been students in college
classes that I've taught, who have
successfully applied at the CIA. They've
gotten in. One of them told me a couple
of weeks ago that she was in a uh
counterintelligence class.
And there was a slide that said, "The
Insider Threat."
And it had a picture of me.
And she said, "Everybody in the class
started to boo."
And the instructor said, "Are you booing
him
or you booing
the slide?"
And they said, "The slide. He's not an
insider threat.
He was the whistleblower.
It was the agency that was the threat."
And she said that in the next running of
the class, they took the slide out.
So, I think that
they probably thought that prosecuting
me would silence me forever.
And in fact, my ex-wife said to me one
time,
"Boy, if they thought this was going to
silence you, they didn't know you at
all."
And I said, "No.
They've given me,
you know, a reason for being.
Now, this is going to be my thing. This
is going to be my life. Civil rights,
civil liberties, and human rights."
And it has. It's been my life.
Mhm.
Yeah, I'll tell you what.
If they had called me
after my initial ABC News interview, in
which I blew the whistle,
and if they had said, "Dog gone you. You
need to shut the [__] up."
I probably would have said, "I'm sorry.
You're right.
I'll drop it."
And that would have been the end of it.
But no, they had to be dicks about it.
>> [laughter]
>> And they had to prosecute me.
And so now, look what happened. John
Brennan was the one who insisted that I
be prosecuted and go to prison. And now
he's going to be prosecuted and he's
going to go to prison.
Mhm.
>> When you think about your work,
the missions you've done,
some of the more emotional visceral
things you've seen,
is there any one person or one face
that you see in your sleep?
>> Yeah, I mean, it may sound cliche at
this point, but but it's Abu Zubaydah.
Abu Zubaydah, the night that we captured
Abu Zubaydah, my entire life changed.
The entire course of the rest of my life
changed. This was the highest level
terrorist up until that point that we
had ever captured.
And he just turned out to be
not the guy we thought he was.
Part of the problem was we didn't know.
We believed he was the number three in
Al-Qaeda.
We didn't know that he had a cousin who
went by the same name, Abu Zubaydah. Abu
Zubaydah's real name is
um Zayn al-Abidin Muhammad Husayn.
He just goes by Abu Zubaydah.
And his cousin went by Abu Zubaydah.
So, we're getting these reports, Abu
Zubaydah's planning an attack in Amman.
Okay, we better inform the Jordanians.
Abu Zubaydah's planning an attack in
Charlotte. Like, Charlotte?
How did he get to Charlotte? Abu
Zubaydah's planning an attack in Riyadh.
Abu Zubaydah's in Billings, Montana,
planning an attack. We're like, "Oh my
god, this guy's a terrorist Superman."
There were two of them.
So, the one that we were after, he was a
bad guy.
He had founded Al-Qaeda's two training
camps in southern Afghanistan. He had
founded the House of Martyrs, Al-Qaeda's
safe house in Peshawar, Pakistan. He was
a logistician for Al-Qaeda. If you
wanted to get into Afghanistan and fight
the Americans, he would get you in,
smuggle you in. If you wanted to leave
and go home, you're tired of the fight,
he would get you a fake passport, get
you home.
But, he was not the Superman that we
thought he was.
He was not
the number three in Al-Qaeda. He was
never even in Al-Qaeda.
And we tortured this guy to within an
inch of his life.
To the point where
there's a footnote in the Senate torture
report saying that Abu Zubaydah will
never be released. He will never have
access to the outside world, ever.
And when he dies at Guantanamo,
we'll cremate his body and throw the
ashes into the Caribbean as if he never
existed.
That's not the American way.
If this guy was really who we said he
was,
charge him with a crime and make him
defend himself.
But, we can't charge him with the crime
because we tortured him.
And so, literally nothing of what he
said
is
we're able are we able to use in court.
None of it's admissible in court.
Um
I was the first
CIA officer, former CIA officer, to call
for his release.
I did it um on the BBC in 2015.
And now I'm in touch with his attorneys.
Wanting to know how I can help
because he should be released. Even if
he's guilty.
He has done 24 years
in the worst possible prison conditions,
having been tortured almost to death.
Even if he's guilty of crimes, he's done
his time.
Let him go.
>> This could be a dumb question.
What's the Arabic word for terrorist?
Well,
we always just use jihadi, which isn't
really terrorist, it's struggler.
But do they call us terrorist?
Probably.
Probably in relation to our
Israel-Palestine policy. Mhm.
Yeah.
Have you spoke to him? No.
No, and I've not written to him either
because he's not permitted to have
access to the outside world. It's almost
impossible even for his own attorneys to
meet with him. They can only meet with
him in the presence of either a CIA
officer or a Pentagon official or both.
Mhm.
Even he drew he's an accomplished
artist.
The night that we captured him, we also
confiscated his diary.
Um, that's a whole different topic, but
in the diary were his sketches and
drawings. He's a gifted artist, gifted.
I remember leafing through it that night
thinking, "Wow, this guy's really
talented."
So, he drew
pictures of his own torture
and the things that they did to him.
And the CIA classified all the pictures
top secret.
So, nobody's ever seen them.
What would you guess would be the worst
one?
Well, did you know the the
conventional wisdom is the worst one is
waterboarding.
And certainly it's horrible, but but I
didn't think it was the worst. I thought
there were two that were worse.
We never killed anybody by waterboarding
them. His heart stopped at one point and
we revived him so he could be tortured
more.
But there were two techniques that I
always believed were worse than
waterboarding. One was the cold cell
where we would chain a prisoner to an
eye-bolt in the ceiling.
So he couldn't sit or lay or get
comfortable in any way.
And strip him naked.
And
chill the cell to 50° F.
And then every hour a CIA officer would
go in the cell and throw ice water on
him.
We killed people with that. With
hypothermia, we killed them. We weren't
authorized to kill people in these
sessions.
We get these cables like, uh
Ibn Shaykh al-Libi unfortunately didn't
make it through the night. He was in the
cold cell. What do we do?
Uh you dig a hole and bury him.
That's awful.
But that's what we did.
The other technique was sleep
deprivation.
>> [gasps]
>> People don't think that sleep
deprivation is any big deal. You know,
again you're chained to that eye-bolt in
the ceiling and you've got these
industrial strength lights right on you.
And then you've got, you know, death
metal on a loop at a volume of 10 24/7.
We know from the American Psychological
Association that people begin to lose
their minds at day seven with no sleep.
Day seven, they begin to die at day nine
because your organs start to fail.
The CIA was authorized to keep people
awake for 12 days.
12 days. We murdered people with that.
Murdered from lack of sleep.
>> Have you ever met anyone that you
suspect enjoyed torture?
>> Yes, I have.
I've met a number of people
over the years
who enjoyed torture. One of them ended
up becoming the director of the CIA.
Gina Haspel
was a senior counterterrorism official
who flew out to the secret site
just to sit in on on session because it
got her rocks off.
In the hall we used to call her Bloody
Gina.
Bloody Gina, can you imagine?
Being a woman
known through your career as Bloody Gina
because you're such a psychopath that
you enjoy watching other people be
tortured and humiliated. What kind of
person is that?
So yeah, there were others that
they would come out of these sessions
like energized. Like, "Whoa!" You know,
"USA!"
That's not normal.
That's just not normal.
But there were a lot of people like
that.
>> What's the comment section of a
ex-CIA officer look like?
>> You know, normally
people are wonderful.
They really are, normally.
And then every once in a while I'll just
get an [__]
And I'm like, "Guy,
it's my [__] page.
You can't come on here and say I'm a
traitor and I need to be put to death."
And so I block people almost every day.
>> Really?
>> Yeah, I have to.
If you want to engage in debate and
disagree with me, awesome. I look
forward to it.
But don't say that you know, you're
going to spread my brains on the
sidewalk, for example.
We're not We're not going to have that
conversation.
I do get a lot
of uh I can't possibly answer all the
DMs. I can't.
Like hundreds a day in addition to the
hundreds of emails.
And most of them are
Most of them are people who just
are
they're in need of psychiatric
intervention.
Yeah, there are a lot of people like
that out there.
>> You get a lot of Cameo requests, too.
>> Oh my god.
>> you broke the record on Cameo.
>> Five years ago my brother-in-law bought
my sister a cameo.
>> Hm. She watches the Real Housewives of
something or other.
>> And
and she loved it. So, I was like vaguely
aware in the back of my mind there's
this thing called Cameo and it's fun.
So, within like a day of my explosion on
TikTok,
uh Cameo reached out and said, "Hey,
have you ever heard of Cameo?" I said,
"Oh, yes, my sister had this Cameo from
my brother-in-law. Would you like to do
it?" I said, "Yeah, yeah, sure. Why
not?"
And I said to my sister,
"I make $400 for an op-ed.
If I could make $400 a month
to replace the op-ed, hey, that would be
good, right?"
The first month I was on Cameo, I broke
the all-time record for the number of
Cameos
>> [laughter]
>> How much do you charge? It's really
cheap, right?
>> I charged 90 I charged $49 and then they
told me to raise it to 99, but the
algorithm changes the price every 15
minutes depending on how busy you are,
how many requests you're getting.
So, I don't think it's ever actually
been at 99, even though that's what I
have it set at. Right now, as we're
sitting here speaking,
I will tell you real quickly,
it is
159.
>> Oh, got you.
>> Yeah.
>> Huh.
Yeah, I mean, but I'm sure you you do a
lot. Like most people like they just
charge $10,000 or 5,000 and then they
just do like
if it hits, but like you want to do a
lot of I think you like it a lot.
>> I enjoy it so much. The CEO of Cameo,
who's an awesome guy, Steven. Steven
flew to DC to take me to dinner that
first night and they gave me this Cameo
jacket that I wear every day.
And it it's just so much fun, but they
told me in the beginning most Cameos are
between like 60 seconds and 90 seconds.
I
can't possibly do one so short.
So, mine are like between 3 minutes and
4 minutes.
>> [laughter]
>> And
there are people
like in the top 10
that I'm
not competing with, but comparing with.
So, I looked at some of them. They're
they're rappers and reality TV stars and
stuff like that. And some of them like
their average cameo is 15 seconds, 20
seconds. But then they have like 2.3
stars out of five. And I have 4.98 stars
out of five because
they'll do cameos like in the backseat
of the car at night. So, it's just
completely black and you can't see and
you know, people are spending
hard-earned money.
And they're asking mostly for Well,
about 50% of them are birthday wishes
and tell me a story.
But the others are asking for advice
or pep talks. And I'll tell you one
thing that's really been touching to me
is
three or four times a week
somebody will message me or email me and
say that I
said something
or I messaged them and I talked them out
of committing su-
which is just
mind-blowing to me.
You know, it's funny we
we get so wrapped up in our own lives.
We don't really think about other
people's suffering.
And um
you know, if somebody reaches out and
says
Let me back up.
I've got a a friend.
Every time we'd have a conversation
he would say, "I'm going to kill myself.
I'm going to kill myself." And I'd say,
"Dude, you've been telling me for years
that you're going to kill yourself.
You're not going to kill yourself.
Then he got in trouble. He decided,
"Okay, he's going to do it. He's going
to kill himself." He drives to a Walmart
because he doesn't want to mess up his
mom's house.
He has a gun. He puts the gun in his
mouth just as an off-duty ATF agent is
pulling into the parking lot to do his
grocery shopping. Sees him with a gun,
pulls his gun, "Drop the gun! Drop the
gun!" Arrests him. Now, my buddy had a
felony conviction at some point years
and years ago. They got him for felon
with a gun. Mandatory minimum 5 years.
So, he calls me one night. I get this
call from from a a jail in Wyoming. I
was like, "What? Who in the world would
be calling me from a jail?" So, I'm
intrigued enough. I answer the call.
It's him. I said, "What the [__] are you
doing in a jail in Wyoming?" And he
tells me, "I was going to kill myself
and I went to the Walmart parking lot."
So, I find him a lawyer. The lawyer gets
him out on bail.
He had a son with his girlfriend and um
she was just so appalled that he had
gotten himself into trouble again. She
wouldn't let him see the the child.
So, he's depressed and he's calling me
every day, "I'm going to kill myself." I
said, "James, you're not going to kill
yourself.
You're going to pick your pick yourself
up by the bootstraps and you're going to
fight this thing."
And then he called me one day.
And he said, "Hey, I got bad news. My
sister lit off a firecracker and she
blew three fingers off." I was like, "Oh
my god, that's terrible news." "Oh, she
was in surgery for like 14 hours and
they attached her fingers back."
I said, "Oh my god, what a terrible
thing."
Two days later, she calls me. And I
said, "Hey, how are your fingers doing?"
And she said, "The fingers are fine. I
got to tell you, James killed himself
last night."
And I was like, "What? I just talked
him. 2 days ago, he sounded great."
And she said he sounded great because he
finally made the decision to do it.
And he was at peace with himself.
But she said the reason I'm calling is
he left a note.
And he said, "Please tell John that I
said I was sorry."
And the reason why I'm still so mad
about this
have you ever heard of the folk singer
Pete Seeger?
Pete is one of the giants of 20th
century American history.
And and one of my idols and role models.
"This land is your land."
Pete made that
uh famous. It's Woody Guthrie song. But
anyway,
Pete wrote dozens of songs that you know
every word to.
He told me one time a story about Phil
Ochs, who was also a gigantic folk
singer of the '60s and '70s.
Pete said he was finishing up a concert
at a at a folk club in uh
in Greenwich Village one night, and he
had to literally run to Grand Central
Station to get the last train of the
night back to Beacon, New York, which is
where he lived.
And as he's packing up his guitar
one of the waitresses said, "Pete, Phil
Ochs is on the phone for you." And he
grabs the phone, he said, "Phil, I can't
talk right now. I got to run to catch
the last train to Beacon. Call me
tomorrow." and hung up.
And Phil Ochs killed himself.
And he said, "That selfish prick will
never know how many people he hurt
by taking his own life that night."
And I never understood that anger
until my friend James killed himself.
And I'm furious with him
5 years after he did it.
Like, doggone you.
Why didn't you call me?
Yeah. Well, anyway,
>> Cuz you answered so many times.
>> So many times.
I went on Facebook and I said, "My
friend James killed himself last night."
And I said, "Please call somebody. Call
me
if you're thinking of killing yourself."
And three of my Facebook friends called
me that night.
I had no idea so many people were
suffering. No idea.
So, you know,
I think we always have to be we have to
remind ourselves to be more aware
of the feelings of others
and not be so wrapped up in our own
lives. It's easy to be wrapped up in
your own life, but we really have to be
cognizant of what other people are
suffering through.
Right.
>> This is how I think I cannot function
unless you are.
>> You're absolutely right.
>> John, you've spent
a good majority of your life serving
America.
Not just the country, but our people.
You've exposed a dark part of the system
when you thought that we've gone too
far.
Many agreed.
Even when it cost you everything.
If every interview, every Tik Tok, every
book you've written, every cameo was
erased from the face of the earth,
>> [gasps]
>> what is the one story from your life
that you would want to leave with the
world?
>> Oh, that's an easy one. Thank you.
That I told the truth.
If we don't have the truth, we don't
have anything.
We really don't. The truth always has a
way of coming out. Sometimes it takes a
long time, years, decades,
but the truth always comes out.
And we should want to be on the right
side of it.
If there's one thing that my children
can be proud of,
it's that I told the truth.
I have lots of faults just like every
other human,
but at least I want to be known for
telling the truth.
And one more.
Aside from the truth or maybe on that
vein,
what's the best piece of advice
someone has given you?
>> When I was in college,
somebody told me that Senator Jennings
Randolph of West Virginia
was listed in the Washington D.C.
telephone book.
And I looked and there he was.
And I called him.
And I said, "Senator Randolph, you don't
know me.
I'm a student at George Washington
University.
And I just wanted to thank you for your
50 years of service to our country."
Going back to Franklin Roosevelt, he was
elected in the election of 1934,
this senator.
And he said, "Why, thank you, young
man."
And he said, "May I offer you some
advice?" And I said, "Senator, anything
you have to say, I'd love to hear it."
And he said, "Always do the right thing.
This city is too full of people who are
willing to do the expedient thing."
And I said, "I'm going to write that
down."
And he says, "You have a good night."
And he hung up.
And I've always remembered it. I
actually did write it down and I stuck
it inside a book, which I still have.
>> Right.
>> Mhm. And you know, it's funny. I was a
little bit starstruck at the time.
But as I've aged and I've accumulated,
you know,
life events of my own,
I realized that just those few words
were really, really important.
It's It's so much easier to do what's
expedient.
It's easier to do what might make us a
little bit of money.
And you come to realize life's not about
the money.
You know, we're all going to end up in
the ground someday.
I I read something that was very
depressing in the Washington Post the
other day.
It said, "We all die two deaths.
We die when we take our last breath,
and we die when our name is spoken for
the last time."
Well,
I don't want my name spoken for a last
time.
I want to be remembered for something.
And
what I want is to be remembered as
someone who told the truth.
Beautiful.
>> [sighs]
>> Well, everyone, uh
this has been your guest, John Kiriakou.
>> Mhm.
>> John, is there anything uh
any platforms you want to shout out
specifically?
>> for asking. Yeah, I'm on I'm on
Instagram, Facebook, and and X, and uh
and LinkedIn. But, I'm launching a new
um podcast in July
on YouTube. If you go to
realjohnkiriakou, I'd really appreciate
it if you would subscribe so that when
we hit the ground running the first week
of July, you're on and you don't miss a
an episode.
>> Number one podcast in the world, I hope.
>> Uh
I hope so.
>> This is the Jack Ryan podcast.
I appreciate you coming on, man.
>> Thank you so much for the invitation.